<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dataviz on Rob Briers</title>
    <link>https://robbriers.github.io/tags/dataviz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dataviz on Rob Briers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Rob Briers</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/dataviz/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Auto kite-diagrams from googlesheets</title>
      <link>https://robbriers.github.io/post/auto-kite-diagrams-from-googlesheets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robbriers.github.io/post/auto-kite-diagrams-from-googlesheets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: package &amp;#39;viridis&amp;#39; was built under R version 3.4.3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://robbriers.github.io/img/millport.png&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every October, we take a party of third year undergraduates to the Isle of Cumbrae for residential field course at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.field-studies-council.org/centres/scotland/millport.aspx&#34;&gt;FSC Millport&lt;/a&gt;. Whilst there, they are immersed in a world of intertidal ecology, looking at influences of habitat characteristics, adaptation and interactions that makes the descriptions and illustrations of Begon or Molles a little more real and apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the work, we look at zonation on both rocky and sandy shores (like a million other student groups!). The class work together to collate data from transects up the shore and examine patterns of distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classic (although some would say not ideal) way of illustrating such zonation patterns is through kite diagrams. Back in the day, we made use of the Fieldworks software which as far as I can determine is no longer available and was rather clunky as well. As we worked in groups across several labs, this also required running around with a USB stick to compile the data from the different groups, before doing the final plotting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://robbriers.github.io/img/rockyshore.png&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a few years and we started to use a shared Google spreadsheet to collate the data instead, which made life a lot easier on that front. The actual kite diagram production was still not straightforward and I experimented with various Excel-based solutions, before starting to work with R code that I found on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I was determined to try and make the process more streamlined, hence the current post. The &lt;code&gt;googlekites&lt;/code&gt; function allows the automatic production of kite diagrams from a shared Google spreadsheet. I can’t claim much credit for this however; the core code for the kite diagram comes from David Hood, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://rpubs.com/thoughtfulbloke/kitegraph&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. All I did was to add in code to wrangle the data from the spreadsheet into a suitable format and add a few bells and whistles to the actual plotting, such as modifying the axis ticks and using better &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/package=viridis&#34;&gt;viridis&lt;/a&gt;-based colours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function has two arguments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sheet_ref&lt;/code&gt;: the full URL to the Google spreadsheet that is being used. The sheet needs to be set to be shared appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;min_abund&lt;/code&gt;: the minimum total abundance of taxa that should be plotted. Taxa with low total numbers are often difficult to interpret in terms of distribution patterns. This defaults to 50; too low a value can result in the plot becoming very crowded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet import is handled by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/package=gsheet&#34;&gt;gsheet&lt;/a&gt; package. I could have used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/package=googlesheets&#34;&gt;googlesheets&lt;/a&gt; package as an alternative, but this has quite a large footprint in terms of dependencies so &lt;code&gt;gsheet&lt;/code&gt; keeps it lightweight. The only other dependency is &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/package=viridis&#34;&gt;viridis&lt;/a&gt;, for the colour-blind friendly colour scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example spreadsheet used can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1pv041th4inXsSRTy8afM0gE14dgeR9TvwmJWEnnC6LQ/edit#gid=0&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It may not have the most logical setup from some perspectives, but it works for us and the code in the function can be easily adapted to other setups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full code for the function is given below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# googlekites function: check out the layout of the data in the spreadsheet
# above before trying to use/adapt this

googlekites&amp;lt;-function(sheet_ref, min_abund=50){
  require(gsheet)
  require(viridis)
  
  # turn off warnings temporarily, as columns do not have headers
  options(warn=-1)
  
  # import data from GoogleSheet
  survey&amp;lt;-gsheet2tbl(sheet_ref)
  
  # remove station row
  survey&amp;lt;-survey[-c(3), ]
  
  # extract taxon names etc (first column), use [[]] notation 
  # to convert to vector
  rn&amp;lt;-survey[[1]]

  # remove column from df
  survey&amp;lt;-survey[-1]
  
  # convert to numeric matrix
  survey&amp;lt;-data.matrix(survey)

  # transpose
  survey&amp;lt;-t(survey)
  
  # revert to dataframe and add column names
  survey&amp;lt;-as.data.frame(survey)
  names(survey)&amp;lt;-rn
  
  # work out summed abundance by station (col 2)
  # survey$Station
  surveysum&amp;lt;-aggregate(survey, by=list(survey[,2]), sum, na.rm=TRUE)

  # remove taxa that are not above min_abund
  surveysum&amp;lt;-surveysum[, -which(colSums(surveysum) &amp;lt; min_abund)]

  # remove group and station columns
  surveysum&amp;lt;-surveysum[, -c(1, 3)]
  
  # rescale the abundances for the plotting of the polygons
  # scaled based on the max abundance of any of the taxa being plotted
  surveysum[,2:ncol(surveysum)] &amp;lt;- (surveysum[,2:ncol(surveysum)] / max(surveysum[,2:ncol(surveysum)]))/2
  
  # copy data for polygon coordinate creation
  surveysum2 &amp;lt;- surveysum
  
  # reverse order for polygons plotting
  surveysum2 &amp;lt;- surveysum2[order(surveysum2[,1], decreasing = TRUE),]
  
  # make values negative
  surveysum2[,2:ncol(surveysum2)] &amp;lt;- surveysum2[,2:ncol(surveysum2)] * -1
  
  # bind data
  surveysum &amp;lt;- rbind(surveysum,surveysum2)
  
  # work out plot dimensions
  leftedge &amp;lt;- min(surveysum[,1])
  rightedge &amp;lt;- max(surveysum[,1])
  bottomedge &amp;lt;- 0
  topedge &amp;lt;- ncol(surveysum) #-1
  
  # save old margins
  oldMargins &amp;lt;- par()$mar
  par(mar=c(5.1,7,2,2.1))
  
  # make blank plot and add axes/ticks
  plot(c(leftedge,rightedge), c(bottomedge, topedge), type= &amp;quot;n&amp;quot;, xlab=names(surveysum)[1], frame.plot=F, yaxt=&amp;quot;n&amp;quot;, ylab=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;)
  axis(1, at=surveysum[,1])
  axis(2, labels=names(surveysum)[2:ncol(surveysum)], font=3, at=1:(ncol(surveysum)-1), las=2, lty=0)
  
  # set up viridis colour sequence
  colours&amp;lt;-viridis(ncol(surveysum)-1, alpha = 1, begin = 0, end = 1, direction = 1, option = &amp;quot;D&amp;quot;)

  # loop through columns, creating polygons
  xValues = surveysum[,1]
  for (i in 2:ncol(surveysum)){
    yValues = i + surveysum[,i] - 1
    polygon(xValues,yValues, col=colours[[i-1]], border=colours[[i-1]])
  }
  
  # reset margins
  par(mar=oldMargins)
  
  # turn warnings back on
  options(warn=0)
}
# end of function&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of use, based on the spreadsheet linked above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# set the values for the two arguments
sheet_ref&amp;lt;-&amp;#39;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1pv041th4inXsSRTy8afM0gE14dgeR9TvwmJWEnnC6LQ/edit#gid=0&amp;#39;

min_abund&amp;lt;-70

# run the function
googlekites(sheet_ref, min_abund)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://robbriers.github.io/post/2017-09-19-auto-kite-diagrams-from-googlesheets_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First field testing will come in three weeks when we are off on the trip again, so there may be a few tweaks as a result afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
