<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conservation on Rob Briers</title>
    <link>/tags/conservation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conservation on Rob Briers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Rob Briers</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/tags/conservation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation planning</title>
      <link>/project/conservation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/conservation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I have had a long-standing interest in applying formal optimisation methods in the evaluation of priorities for conservation in relation to protected area planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/fife_birds.png&#34; alt=&#34;fife birds&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;spatial-methods-of-protected-area-planning&#34;&gt;Spatial methods of protected area planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work initially focused largely on terrestrial ecosystems, and specifically the development of approaches to site selection that involved consideration of spatial criteria. The spatial configuration of protected sites is an important consideration for species persistence and I developed both heuristic and integer programming-based methods for incorporating this, in conjunction with &lt;a href=&#34;http://ace.illinois.edu/directory/h-onal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof Hayri Onal&lt;/a&gt;. For example papers, see &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/connectivity/&#34;&gt;Briers 2002&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/connected/&#34;&gt;Onal &amp;amp; Briers 2006&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/salmon_farm.png&#34; alt=&#34;salmon farm&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;marine-spatial-planning&#34;&gt;Marine spatial planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently I have developed an interest in marine spatial planning (MSP) developments. Marine space is complex and commonly multi-use, requiring different approaches to the designation of space. See for example &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/zoning_scheme/&#34;&gt;McWhinnie et al 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/mangroves.png&#34; alt=&#34;mangroves&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mangrove-protection&#34;&gt;Mangrove protection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also begun work to combine formal optimisation methods with data on carbon stores and risk factors in mangrove ecoystems to look at approaches to prioritisation for protection and restoration. This is linked to empirical and modelling work detailed in the &lt;a href=&#34;/project/spatial-ecology/&#34;&gt;Spatial Ecology&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
